foreign
hello and welcome it's March 29th 2023
we're here in active guest stream number
40.1 with Banya Visa we're going to be
hearing a presentation in the first
section and then having a discussion so
thank you Vania for joining again really
looking forward to your presentation
thank you very much
um so this presentation is based on a
preprint that can be found at Phil
archive
and this is
work in progress
and uh probably or hopefully
upload a revised version of this
preprint in a few weeks
so if you're watching this or if you're
reading the pre-print and have any
comments or questions feedback is very
much welcome
and I'm also again grateful for having
the opportunity to present here because
I'm really looking forward to the
discussion and any comments that people
may have while watching this video so do
contact me if you have questions or
comments
now I want to start this presentation
with an idea from this wonderful Novella
by tatchiang the life cycle of software
objects
and if you're not familiar with the
novella it doesn't matter so there's
some digital entities or
digians as they're called in the novella
who
um
at first live in a purely virtual
environment so these are virtual
entities like virtual pets and human
users can interact with them in a
virtual environment
then in some passages
of the novella there are scenes in which
some digins are as it were downloaded
from this purely virtual environment
and are implemented in a physically
embodied robot so the
program that is running on in within
this computer simulation and is
controlling the purely virtual body
is then downloaded into a physically
embodied computer
and is controlling a physical robot
which can interact with its physical
environment non-virtual environment
in the same way in which the virtual
agent the virtual Digi and
interacts with a virtual environment
and I find this idea really fascinating
and Powerful so the novella suggests
that these virtual entities are
conscious and that they can switch
back and forth as it were between this
purely virtual environment and uh
physical non-virtual environment
and the idea is that the
these entities remain conscious when
they're in the robot but also went there
and returned to the virtual environment
and to some people it may be unintuitive
or counter-intuitive
that a purely virtual entity and a
simulated environment can be conscious
or maybe some of these people will find
it less counter-intuitive
to imagine a conscious robot
and
so the the
um idea is fascinating to me because it
suggests that well if you can switch
back and forth from the virtual
environment
to the physical environment
and in the other direction and really
doesn't matter where the the software is
implement the system remains conscious
and I will come back to this idea at the
end of my presentation
and we will see what the the account
that I'm presenting here suggests with
respect to this scenario
also this is the overview of my
presentation which which is based on the
preprint I'm just omitting a lot of
details
so start by saying just a few things
about the pre-energy principle then I
will ask what is the difference between
an unconscious simulation of a conscious
system and a conscious computational
system on other words what's the
difference between what is called weak
and strong artificial Consciousness so
strong artificial consciousness
is conscious isn't actually conscious uh
artificial system and weak artificial
Consciousness is constituted by a an
artificial system that maybe behaves as
if it were conscious or that simulates
the conscious being but is not actually
conscious
and I'm interested in the question
what's the difference
and a particular version of this
question is whether a computer
simulation in a computer with a
phenomenon architecture can be conscious
so I start with the free energy
principle and
um I don't want to get go into the
details so we
start with the with a description of a
physical system so the x is the the
physical system and the fundamental
assumption is that the Dynamics of
physical dynamics of this system can be
decomposed into two components so we on
one hand have a deterministic flow term
F and then some noise term
stochastic noise terms so we end up with
a stochastic differential equation which
describes how the physical system
evolves over time the further assumption
is that we can decompose the states of
the system into internal States mu
external States ETA sensory States as an
active States a which together so
sensory and active States together
constitute the blanket States B
and
this then is a particular system
that can be partitioned into internal
Annex external States separated by
blanket States
and a further assumption is that the
dynamics of this system can also be
partitioned in the following sense that
we can
decompose this flow term into individual
flow terms for the different states so
we have a flow term for internal States
mu and can also describe the Dynamics of
internal States in terms of software
differential equation here
okay so these are just technical
fundamental assumptions made by the free
energy principle but then the
interesting thing starts here when we
look at how we else we can describe
internal States and the Dynamics of
internal States so the idea is
that we can map internal States mu to I
to probability distributions so this is
your formulation in terms of states and
then the idea is that at every point in
time
the
system will be in certain States so
there will be internal States relative
to each time point and we can map
each of these states to start to some
probability distribution Q of external
States given blanket States
okay so we can do that but then the
question is why should we do that and
the idea is that maybe we can redescribe
the flow term which is essential for
characterizing the Dynamics of internal
States
can we redescribe these flow terms in
terms of the probability distribution
encoded by internal States
and the free energy principle answers
yes we can rewrite this term in terms of
a variational free energy functional
which specifies how the probability
distribution Q which is parallel
parameterized by mu
changes over time
so we can re formulate the physical
dynamics of internal staves we can
rewrite the flow term in terms of
variational free energy
or in terms of minimizing variational
free energy with respect to a
probability distribution encoded by
internal States
and this is then called Bayesian
mechanics and it's called Bayesian
mechanics well because minimizing
variation of the energy involves
minimizing it Divergence term between
the
internally encoded probability
distribution q and a posterior of a
external States given blanket States
okay
so
to to sum this up I will give these
ideas some some labels so I've already
talked about the physical Dynamics and
this these are the Dynamics of a
particular system
described by stochastic differential
equation involving a flow term and a
noise term
and recall that a particular system is a
system that can be partitioned into
internal external and blanket States
and then
according to the for energy principle we
can redescribe these physical Dynamics
in terms of as computational Dynamics
we can reformulate them in terms of a
description of the system's internal
States mu as performing approximative
Bayesian inference by minimizing
variation of free energy with respect to
a probability density encoded by mu so
right in in short we can reformulate the
physical Dynamics as a computational
process that involves
the form of Bayesian inference
now a further assumption that I want to
make here is that we can capture the
computational correlates of
Consciousness in terms of the
computational Dynamics as described by
the free energy principle
so yeah the computer computational
corals of Consciousness or cccs are
defined as a computational dynamics of a
physical system
of a conscious physical system as
specified by the free energy principle
okay so this is not just any physical
system it's a conscious physical system
forgot to add this on the slide all
right so given these initial assumptions
and definitions
can we say something about the
difference between weak and strong
artificial consciousness
and I think we can
um so
let's start with the the idea of a
computational quality of Consciousness
um computations are medium independent
so it's plausible that a digital
computer can Implement computational
corals of consciousness
well then the question if we want to
distinguish weak from strong artificial
Consciousness is
is every system that implements ccc's
conscious or
do systems have to implement these
computations in the right way and what
would that be
okay so to
better understand this question I find
it useful to look at this diagram and
um see where we started so we have a
description of a control systems
physical Dynamics
in the bottom left and then according to
the free energy principle we can
reformulate this redescribe this as some
computational Dynamics
and by assumption these include the
computational correlates of
consciousness
and they must be implemented by the
physical dynamics of the conscious
system now given that these are medium
independent properties they can also be
instantiated by other systems and here
I'm assuming that there can also be that
these computations can also be
implemented by a digital computer
and the digital computer as a physical
system has some physical Dynamics and if
we can apply the free industry principle
to it we can reformulate these physical
Dynamics as computational Dynamics
and so then the question becomes do
these computational Dynamics do they
include
the computational correlates of
Consciousness whatever they are
so this is a crucial question that we
have to answer if we want to know what
the difference between weak and strong
artificial Consciousness is maybe there
is no difference
so before I present an argument
to the effect that in general the
computational Dynamics of a digital
computer will not
entail The computational Columns of
consciousness
before I present this argument I will
present some observations on the
apprenticeship principle so note that
systems that conform to the French
principles sustain their existence by
minimizing variation of free energy
but the reverse does not hold so you can
run simulations
of agents that minimize variation of
free energy and you can do that
on a computer which does not thereby
sustain its existence so it would
continue to exist regardless of whether
it runs these simulations or not
okay just to
illustrate this with a quotation which
may be familiar to many so
this is by press mat out many theories
in the biological sciences are answers
to the question what must things do in
order to exist the free energy principle
turns this question on its head and asks
if things exist what must they do more
formally if we can Define what it means
to be something can we identify the
physics or dynamics that a thing must
possess
and Jacob Howie
puts a similar Point as follows for
energy principle analyzes the concept of
existence of particular self-organizing
systems so the idea is that continuing
to exist sustaining one's existence
means minimizing variational free energy
and so any processes that contribute to
minimizing variational frenzy and
thereby contribute to the sustained
existence of the system
foreign
such processes can also be implemented
in other ways
by different systems which do not
thereby sustain their existence on this
I want to suggest is a crucial
difference between
systems are merely simulate
Contra systems and systems that actually
are conscious
okay so and
I will hopefully clarify this idea in in
a moment by presenting an argument but
before that I need a definition so
um
um I want to introduce a notion of
intrinsic computation
and these are just computations that
contribute to the sustained existence of
the systems so these are the
computations that figure in the
computational reformulation
of the system's physical Dynamics
according to the free energy principle
and intrinsic here means these
computations are Observer independent so
it's not the case that we as observers
say okay we can interpret the system as
performing these computations or it's
useful for us to use them as
computational devices the idea is that
these computations are processes that
are intrinsic to the system that only
depend on properties of the system
itself and not on relations that the
system has to observe us or to other
beings
okay
um
so here's the argument which
in a way is already contained in the
preprint but
um I
did not formulate the argument of this
explicit way so I'm grateful to Tommy
corbach Who provided some comments on my
pre-print and to also
suggested a or um a reconstruction of
the argument that I'm presenting in the
pre-print and uh this formulation here
is based on atomic's suggestions and I
hope this clarifies the argument that
I'm
putting forward developing in the
pre-print
okay so the first assumption and the
argument is
a version of computationalism about
Consciousness and the idea is that
causal roles that characterize
phenomenal Consciousness are medium
independent and can be captured in terms
of computation
these are computational correlates of
consciousness
so the idea is that Consciousness does
not require a particular type of
substrate it can be in principle can be
realized by a different types of system
as long as
these systems implement the right
computations so this assumption as I am
intended does not entail that
implementing the right computations is
sufficient for being conscious and see
it just meant as a necessary condition
[Music]
and the idea is that there are
informative interesting computational
correlates of consciousness
and they can in principle be
are formed implemented by different
types of system
then comes the second assumption
According to which every conscious
system and its computational correlates
can be described by a mechanical theory
that conforms to the free energy
principle so this is an assumption about
the scope of the free energy principle
and it's at least clear that the free
energy principle is intended to have a
very wide scope that's not meant just to
apply to a human brain it's not just
meant to apply to living systems but
it's
meant to apply to a very wide class of
self-organizing systems
and
um this idea or this intention that the
free energy principle has a very wide
scope
is also evidenced by the fact that
recent formulations and recent
developments
in research on the free energy
principles seek to relax certain
assumptions that were made in previous
version so as to make the free energy
principle applicable to a very wide
class of systems and not for instance
just to systems in
non-equilibrium steady state
for instance just as one example
all right um
so and the idea is that we can apply the
free energy principle to conscious
systems and that means we can move from
a description of the physical Dynamics
to a description of computational
Dynamics and these will include
computational correlates of
consciousness
okay then the third assumption makes a
connection between intrinsic computation
and Consciousness a system is conscious
only if it sustains its existence by
virtue of the computational correlates
it's it realizes such computation
callers of Consciousness are intrinsic
computations
computations that contribute to the
sustained existence of the system
so if a system
follows certain
or Implement certain physical Dynamics
which under the fep
can be described as computational
dynamics that entail computational
currents of Consciousness whatever they
are then the system's conscious
but it's only conscious if it's in this
direction so in principle it's possible
to implement the same computational
processes without being conscious
and this is
in becomes clear in a conclusion or as
described by conclusion one it's
possible to instantiate computational
Columns of Consciousness in the physical
system without instantiating
Consciousness namely if realizing the
computation of correlates
of Consciousness does not contribute to
the sustained existence of the system so
assuming that a digital computer can
perform the computations that
characterize consciousness
in conscious systems
it's likely according to this proposal
it's likely that the computer will not
thereby be conscious because it could
Implement different computations it
really doesn't matter what computations
it performs it will continue to exist as
a physical system
regardless of the computational
processes that it implements
so it does not
sustain its existence by virtue of the
computations it performs
all right
um and a
condition that is entailed by this is
that from the point of view of the free
energy principle of computation of the
physical system is intrinsic if it
matches the physical
the system's physical Dynamics
um
and this will be
important also for the question about
Consciousness in in computer simulations
so um the second conclusion that I want
to draw here is that computers with a
Von Neumann architecture cannot
Implement intrinsic computations because
their physical Dynamics it uses a causal
flow that is different from the causal
Flow entailed by the computational
Dynamics so there's no match between the
physical and the computational Dynamics
or between the
physical Dynamics and other computations
that are performed within the computer
simulation
well unpack this in the third part of my
presentation so could there be
Consciousness in a computer simulation
computer with a classical architecture
so um this is an idea that uh
already presented and previous works so
in a system that conforms to the free
energy principle there's a basic flow
from internal States via active states
to external States and from external
States via sensory states to internal
States
so we have these circular Dynamics and
in a computer with a Von Neumann
architecture the basic causal flow is a
bit different so we have
um memory and we have a central
processing unit
and the units that store the values of
the different variables of internal that
that stand for internal external and
blanket States
they are in the memory unit and there's
no direct causal interaction between
these units but it's always mediated by
the CPU
um so that's the basic idea and
therefore there's a difference in a
closer flow and I cannot this means that
the physical dynamics of the computer
does not have a or the if we want to
reformulate the physical dynamics of the
computer
in terms of minimizing variation free
energy we end up with something that
cannot match
um the
that that we end up with computational
processes that cannot be identical to
the computations that are simulated by
the computer
um because then there would have to be a
match between the
states that
represent the
probability distributions encoded by
internal States and the internal States
themselves
okay so from this I suggest we can
derive two necessary conditions for
Consciousness one is the flow condition
the causal flow of a physical system's
computational Dynamics which realize
um
which may realize
computational correlates of
Consciousness must match the causal flow
of the systems physical Dynamics
and then there's a second condition
which I call the existential condition
physical system sustains existence by
virtue of the
by virtue of
realizing computational correlates of
consciousness
um so if it's a conscious physical
system then this is the case
all right
um just a few observations or notes
about this so A system can satisfy the
first the flow condition without thereby
satisfying the existential conditions so
there's the existential condition is
stronger than the flow condition
um but if a system satisfies the
existential conditions then it also
satisfies the flow conditions
um
and not all systems that satisfy both of
these conditions are conscious in other
words neither of them
are sufficient for Consciousness these
are really just strictly necessary
conditions for consciousness
all right that's me uh
return to the the idea that are
presented in the beginning beginning
from touching's Novella so
from the point of view of the account
that I presented here is it possible to
download Virtual entity to a robot and
will it be conscious
um or can it be conscious in the
simulation
um so I'm I should just assume here that
these systems satisfy the flow condition
or first condition so
um assuming that this is a very special
computer simulation in which the
physical states that represent internal
external and blanket states that these
physical States also directly causally
interact with each other
um
and
um according to
the
account proposed here the computer
simulation that there would still not be
Consciousness in the computer simulation
because the computer does not sustain
its its existence by virtue of
Performing these computations it could
also run different simulations
which do not involve these digital
entities
and it would continue to exist so
according to this the account presented
here there would not be consciousness
in this system
and if we download the
part of the program that controls the
virtual agent and download it to a
physically embodied robot because that
robot be conscious well in principle it
could if
the robot sustains its existence by
virtue of Performing the computations
that are also performed by the computer
simulation
and um now this result might be a bit
strange because contrary to what the
novella suggests
it would suggest that the system cannot
switch back and forth between the
virtual and the physical non-virtual
environment without losing consciousness
and
I admit that this is a very that is a
kind of counter-intuitive implication
but maybe
it only seems counter-intuitive maybe
it's not technically possible to
download a virtual entity which was
trained in a purely virtual environment
and and
um and download it to implement it in a
physical robot
and thereby allowing the physical robot
to interact with its environment in the
same way as a virtual entity can
interact with a virtual environment so I
know that
in robotics there's a certain strategy
to uh to train robots or to
um
yeah develop the controller of
the the physical robot naming that you
first train it in a virtual and a
simulated environment and then you
use that to control the robot maybe this
only works for robots that have kind of
have certain limitations in their
sensory motor abilities maybe it doesn't
work for highly sophisticated robots
that are more like conscious
organisms which can react adaptively and
very flexible in a flexible way
um can interact flexibly with the
environment on the basis maybe of
effectively guided effectively shaped
representations so this would be a maybe
an empirical hypothesis derived from my
account that this strategy
um this symptom real strategy of
simulating an entity in a virtual
environment and then applying that to a
physical entity the the prediction would
be that this has will at some point
reach limits and will not be successful
if on the other hand this hypothesis
or this prediction will turn out to be
false I'm I think we should reconsider
the account that I'm presenting here
okay let me conclude
um I've asked what is the difference
between weak and strong artificial
Consciousness and the suggestion is that
it's about intrinsic computation that's
the difference
um actually conscious systems sustain
their existence at least in part by
virtue of performing certain
computations and a mere simulation of a
conscious system
does not thereby sustain its existence
it could also perform different
computations and still continue to exist
this condition entails the flow
condition which is important for the
second question called a computer
simulation in the computer with a
phenomenon architecturally conscious no
because it violates the flow condition
okay isn't an ad for the Journal of
philosophy and the mind Sciences which
I'm running together with Sasha thing
Jennifer wind and Regina fabri
and I thank you for your attention
a awesome thank you I'm just
getting my video back in the game
um while I'm
getting everything
back on the Stream
first just thank you for the
presentation and uh wanted to pick up
with that robotics
intro and conclusion
to what extent does the embodiment in
the robot matter beyond the ability of
the virtual simulation to do things like
eject the CD drive or ultimately do
physical things just not the kinds of
physical things that we see
human children do like play with toys
um when you were do when you were
thinking about the virtualized
simulation simulation were you thinking
about one that had no access to sensors
and actuators or what happens when
the digital simulation also has access
in some limited way to
the ability to sense and act on the
outside world
if you have any thoughts
sorry about that on the stream it was
audible but not to you so I see but now
I've resolved the zoom so we can
from your Consciousness perspective
consider it a new question so I just
wanted to to pick up with that robotics
example
um
a digital simulation may still have
sensors engaging with the world and may
still be able to undertake actuation if
only something like flipping a switch on
a processor so what exactly about the
embodiments do you think matters
for it to have that kind of adaptivity
and maybe even open-endedness and
learning that you pointed to as an
important property
yeah
um good question so
um it
um I think there are many different
aspects that you're touching upon are
let me start with this one so I um
mentioned my correspondence with atomic
callback and one thing that he suggested
was that
um
couldn't we regard a language model as a
system that has certain sensory motor
abilities so it can interact with a
physical environment via a
linguistic interface so it receives text
as input and it outputs text as it
outputs text and
um
can't we regard this as sense
as as
sensing and acting and
um
so this this I think is um
similar to one of the aspects that your
question touches upon so what is it
about the the embodiment and can that be
different forms of embodiment that might
still lead to
Consciousness and I don't have a full
reply to this just um two things that um
I would mention here the first is that
there are certainly some analogies
between what a language model does when
it interacts with a user and a system
that maybe an organism that interacts
with its environment via
perception and action
but there are also some dis analogies
so when it comes to interacting with the
environment
for a when an organism interacts with
its environment the their temporal
constraints
um it's really important that it
um
does the right thing at the right time
and reacts fast enough and so on and for
a language model that does not play a
big role
um so there's one difference
and then there's also a difference in
the format of the representations
and in principle you could say okay why
does this matter and
um maybe in the end it doesn't but I
just want to mention that there's some
crucial this analogies that I think
would be important to take into
consideration and evaluate
then uh that's the question okay
is there something about these more
low-level sensory motor skills that is
crucial when it comes to consciousness
now on the one hand we know that a an
organism can be conscious without having
any language skills without being able
to
speak or understand language
and so this this is why when it comes to
functions of Consciousness for instance
people don't look for or usually don't
look for linguistic abilities but more
for sensory motor abilities or forms of
learning that enable or improve
interaction with the world
and
so that this is one thing but of course
in principle
it could still be that A system that
lacks these low level
low level skills is conscious
but then I would say if if it's possible
to be conscious without having these
sensory motor skills then it's not
really about any
ability
for interaction with an environment that
a system is conscious but then it's
merely because of some internal
computations that the system performs so
if you're thinking about
um
systems that might be islands of
awareness systems that don't receive any
sensory input and don't produce any
motor output
then
it's I I wouldn't want to rule out that
such systems are conscious and these
such systems don't have any ways of
interacting with their environment so
I'm happy to
accept that
um
the that interaction with the
environment is not required for
Consciousness and but coming back to
language models this would mean that
being able to interact with users using
language is similarly not required for
Consciousness so I would say if such a
system is conscious then it's not
because of its ability to interact with
the environment because of but because
of the internal processes
and
um
the what what may be crucial is not the
actual interaction with the environment
but just the potential for interaction
with the physical environment
and then it might and in principle it
might might very well be that a language
model
can facilitate interaction with the
physical environment for instance if
it's
connected to a physically embodied robot
and I mean there's research going on
um on on such things
researchers who try to improve the
abilities of their robots by connecting
them or
interfacing them with a language model
which can help translate commands into
motor sequences and
um so what this suggests is that yeah
maybe there are some
crucial
types of representation or computational
processes that are actually already
implemented in language models or in
other systems that don't really
not not directly interact with the
physical environment and I'm happy to
accept that
but I would add that according to the at
least according to the proposal that I
I've presented here you need something
more for that and you you need really
um the the
so it's it's not sufficient to just
Implement these computations
but they must have a meaning for the
system itself in a sense that the system
will sustain its existence by virtue of
these processes if it is connected to
the real physical environment
now um maybe that I've not addressed
every aspect of your question so feel
free to
[Music]
um restate your question or oh it's
great it got to a great place because I
wanted to follow up with this intrinsic
computation concept
so you mentioned that their Observer
independent to the extent that anything
or any process can can be and that these
are the kinds of processes that actually
enable
the
um Persistence of that thing according
to the fep
and so
I was thinking about this first in a
bottom up way like this is the firmware
this is the Linux kernel this is the
kind of enabling software
that is supporting potentially
extraneous higher order functions and
that is allowing some kind of separation
or delineation between what we could say
are like the vital and intrinsic like
almost the homeostatic functions
and then second order functions
but then I thought about the ecology
that the computation is deployed in and
so let's just say that the software
um
is being the the software simulation is
being used in a scientific context or to
run Photoshop
and another cognitive agent
keeps that simulation alive
because it's performing some function
and so from that bottom up sense the
Photoshop program is not the Linux
kernel so it's not like the photo like
the Photoshop
in principle is not sustaining the
Persistence of the entity in a bottom-up
fashion however
in deployment
it actually becomes
a necessary condition
imposed externally
so and that will also be extremely
Observer dependent or subjective
so how do we think about
um in standard
modern computers or in wet wear
what are these intrinsic computations
thank you that's um that's a great
question and
um so
[Music]
I can say more about intrinsic
computation in a moment but just one
comment before that so I think you're
touching on a very important issue and
that's the question
what is a system in the first place so
if we want to
[Music]
consider the question what
kinds of entities can be conscious when
we have to first say okay what what are
the entities that we're looking in at in
the first place
what are these things and
why can't we
look at a piece of software or some
process that is running a an app that a
user is using
um what was the example that you gave
Photoshop or
something so
um why can't we regard Photoshop and a
particular instance of this software as
a system
which exists for some time and it will
continue to exist if it's useful for a
human human being and it's useful by
virtue of the computation where the
computations that are realized by it and
so can't we say that the system sustains
its existence by virtue of the
computations that it performs and so
that that's um I think a very
crucial question because it's so
fundamental so what is a a system and
currently I think that the free energy
principle is sufficient to answer this
question
but it may be that it's still too
General so I mean the the conscious the
the French principle gives us an answer
to the question if something exists what
must it do and so we we it analyzes this
notion of uh the continued existence of
self-organizing systems and
um maybe it does apply to the processes
that Implement Photoshop in the computer
of a human being who
uses this software
and if that's the case then I think
um we have to add some further
constraints
to or
yeah
it may be necessary to add some further
constraints on the kinds of systems
that we want to regard as potentially
conscious or that we want to consider
when it comes to the question
what kinds of systems can be conscious
and one just one suggestion or idea that
I think would be worthwhile to explore
here is to
investigate to what extent something
like the free energy integrated
information Theory
May complement the free energy principle
and this regard
because
integrated information Theory
has a very strong emphasis on the notion
of existence
of what it means to exist what it means
to be what it means to intrinsically
exist as it were not just in the eye of
a beholder
and maybe we we need to add constraints
from something like integrated
information Theory which will then tell
us what
types of systems really exist and then
maybe it would say okay the processes
that are
implementing
Photoshop in this computer
don't really exist in an intrinsic sense
um yeah so this would be that what would
then be my suggestion to add some
constraints but of course you could say
well no
um such constraints are completely
unnecessary we don't need to exclude
certain systems
um and we can regard
the processes that Implement Photoshop
as
um
real a real system that sustains its
existence
but my
intuition would be
at least currently that such processes
would at least in a classic system with
a classical
Hardware would be too scattered and
um there would be so many
physical processes interfering as it
were
that it's
it you can regard this as a separate
thing which is distinct from other
things that are happening in the
computer
[Music]
but I
would say this is more an observer
dependent property those
processes
there that so entangled with other
processes in the physical system that
they are not particular systems
in the sense of the free energy
principle
awesome and again kind of Journeys us to
another question about the
topological or geometric
concordances between physical and
computational Dynamics and it made me
think of a few different kinds of
systems the Von Neumann architecture
described with the CPU and the Ram
regular desktop computer situation
of course we have unconventional
Computing paradigms Quantum and analog
computers
we have the brain and the SPM package in
which statistical inferences help us
model how brain regions that aren't
connected through for example axons can
still have an edge in a Bayesian graph
they could still have a causal effective
or a functional connectivity without
being structurally connected and vice
versa and then to kind of bring it back
to the computer and what you brought up
about whether or not those processes
would be too scattered
what about a computer
either a distributed computing cluster
or a strict virtualization scheme on the
computer such that certain variables
were isolated
would it be enough
for the system to have some kind of
constraint again through a physical
networked
layout or through a virtualized
system
so that the computational flow and the
causal flow
could be played with in a different way
and then how would we know what would we
be looking for surely not simply um
test retest accuracy or efficiency in
some way that's not what Consciousness
is so I mean it really comes down to
what are we looking for or talking about
if we did have the ability to design
different systems that did have
different overlap with their
computational and structural aspects
yeah oh great question so
um
I think it's very important to look at
different types of computer architecture
different uh types of Hardware
[Music]
um and you mentioned some so there's
actually
um something that was
um
pointed out to me by Johannes Kleiner so
here
pointed me to the notion of
computation and memory or something
similar and if I understand that
correctly it um
is a slight departure from the the
Neumann architecture because you're
actually do computations within the
memory unit so it's not that you have
additional memory units within the CPU
but you perform computations in the
memory unit itself
um
which would be a way of satisfying the
flow constraint the flow condition
that I mentioned and similarly there may
be other architecture Maybe neuromorphic
Hardware
that also could Implement
simulations in a way that satisfies the
flow condition
and as I pointed out in the presentation
the flow condition is just one necessary
condition which is weaker than the
existential condition so all of these
systems even if they satisfy the flow
condition were not thereby also satisfy
the stronger existential condition
but as
may have become clear I am not
completely certain about this
existential condition or rather
um there may be some
ways in which one can
describe what's going on in such systems
that you can actually say okay the
processes that Implement these
computations they are
systems particular systems to which the
free energy principle can be applied
even if
maybe the
material on which these processes run
is not directly affected by these
computational processes or maybe the if
we think about maybe neuromorphic
computer chips maybe the chips
themselves
they will continue to exist no matter
what computations they perform
but if what's going on
if the activity that implements the
computations within such a chip
is sophisticated enough or has certain
properties maybe this activity can be
regarded as
a an instance of a particular system to
which the free energy principle can be
applied so I'm not completely certain
about this and I think this is something
that has to be clarified
um yeah I am
maybe maybe it will be useful also to
see what people are actually working on
the forensic principle
what would say about this
but that's very important point
yeah a few things that makes me think of
first is kind of like the hard problem
of virtualization or something in that
some modification of of a hard or easy
question
um and then also about the difference
between a case where the material
substrate of computation is its own
self-referent sustainer
and another case in which the material
basis of a computation is projecting
let's just say a non-equilibrium steady
state
like a holograph
or or it's creating robots it's spinning
out robots or it's doing 3D printing
so in that situation depending on how
the system boundaries are modeled
um
the viability of one part maybe even
like it's kind of semantic germline
is required for the continued
propagation of some other part of this
persistent system but that part is
actually disposable even though it's the
embodiments
[Music]
I'll I'll go to a question in the um
live chat and also I think it was a mem
computing was was the memory based
computer yeah and agree there's a lot of
interesting um threats there so
um Ali asks a question in the chat he
wrote what about understanding if we
Define understanding as a kind of
correlation or mapping between spaces of
semantic possibilities can we say that
large language models do indeed
understand their prompts and outputs and
this understanding in this sense require
or entail Consciousness or vice versa
so with understanding as a map among
semantic spaces what can we say about
llms in understanding and what is the
relationship between understanding and
consciousness
thank you and that's a very good or
these are very good questions
and um
of course it depends on on the notion of
understanding and if we
conceive of understanding as
um yeah as a way of grasping inferential
relations or associative relations
between different Notions if we
um and so that certainly is some some
form of understanding that
um large language models have they can
relate Concepts to one another and uh
their representations of
um Concepts in a vector space
with those
some important parts of the structure of
conceptual spaces
of of our language so in in this sense
they do understand some things
and then there are other forms of
understanding and
um
I wish I would say something in a moment
but um because that's a bit more
complicated and I I cannot say as much
about it I think but um the question
whether understanding entities
Consciousness or understanding in the
um sense you mentioned I would say it
does not entail does not require
consciousness so you you kind of have
that without consciousness
and um
another question is well does
Consciousness require some other form of
understanding Maybe
and I or at least my proposal here would
suggest that yes there is some form of
understanding that is required by
consciousness
and this is an understanding which
is related to
knowing what things in the world some
words or representations refer to so
this requires that you actually have a
concept of
there being a world of which you are a
part and I don't think that large
language models understand that they are
things in the world
they don't know that there is something
out there of which they are a part
and
I think that's
crucial for a a certain form of
understanding
um and
in order for certain things to be
meaningful for you
you must somehow have a concept of
of the the world
and and a sense of that that you're part
of this world and how you relate to
things in the world and so on
now
um
this I I think is required for some form
of understanding
and I think it's also required for
Consciousness at least according to the
proposal that I presented here and the
idea is that if a system not only has
some internal representations that it
manipulates but if by virtue of doing so
it sustains its existence then this puts
some very con strong constraints on what
the system will do with these
representations
so
[Music]
um
if you
if you think about a a self-driving car
um and and principle it may compute all
sorts of things and it will not have a
meaning for the system for the car
itself but if these processes are
realized in a way that the system
systems continued existence depends on
these computations and this puts some
more constraints on what it can do with
these internal representations
and which
will give such a system maybe some form
of Common Sense and
um
allowing it to
draw certain inferences and avoiding
other inferences and so on so
um that would be my
um
hypothesis that there's a certain form
of understanding that requires
these uh that also requires these the
conditions that I think are necessary
for consciousness
hmm
in that I hear a shift from
semantics and semantic embeddings to
true semiosis and the abductive process
of generation of embedded meaning so
it's very
um interesting
okay a few more questions
one
you've been writing
excellent and diverse papers on
different mathematical formalisms of
Consciousness for some years now
so how have you seen the empirical side
and the theoretical side of scientific
study of consciousness
developing in the last several years and
how do you believe that the current
inflection points in artificial
intelligence are like re-contextualizing
or modifying your agenda or bringing
different relevance to your work
um yeah that's a good question and
in general I would say that I mean
there's there's been since the 90s has
been an explosion of empirical work on
consciousness
[Music]
um
partly also due to certain methods that
were and paradigms that were developed
and imaging technology that improved and
so on so we have better ways of
empirically studying consciousness
and
so in the past years as
in or decades a lot of empirical data on
Consciousness has been gathered and many
things have been found out and
I think that two reasons
for which
many people are now
driven to
theoretical approaches again or looking
more closely at theoretical
approaches the first is that data alone
doesn't give you understanding so you
need ways of interpreting data and
constraining experiments and so on
and I I think a
some evidence for this is are these um
recent adversarial collaborations in
which proponents of different
uh theories of consciousness
team up design experiments that would
lead to or could lead to evidence which
more strongly favors one but not the
other Theory
and part of why such adversarial
collaborations are needed or
um are
perceived as necessary by some is that
in previous years
people working with certain theoretical
assumptions in mind or with some with
their pet Theory
maybe a global workspace Theory they've
been
um
or other theories of course they've then
been looking for evidence what that
would confirm their theoretical
assumptions and maybe designing
experiments in a way that is more likely
to yield certain kinds of evidence or
confirming evidence
supporting evidence for their own
theoretical assumptions so
um realizing that in order to make
progress and constrain also the class of
theories that you have realizing that
it's important to do more rigorous
experiments and explore ways in which
you can actually find also find evidence
that this confirms certain theoretical
assumptions
that I think
um
is one of the motivations Behind These
adversary collaborations and also also
makes people a bit more self-conscious
of the theoretical assumptions that
they're making
um yeah then another big issue is of
course that the scope of empirical and
theoretical approaches has to be
expanded we now have good evidence that
many animals that were previously
thought to be unconscious actually are
conscious
animals such as
octopuses and there's at least reason to
take the hypothesis seriously that some
insects may also be conscious
maybe bees are conscious
and
in order to make progress here
theoretical approaches are needed to
help
structure debates and determine what
kind of evidence would be
supportive for certain
hypotheses
or
um which type of kinds of evidence would
be relevant to answer the distribution
question which entities which animals
are conscious
so that's one thing and then of course
you mentioned uh progress in Ai and
people are now
seriously considering what artificial
systems might be conscious and whether
some existing systems might actually
already be conscious
and we need theories to
to make progress on this or maybe not
not necessarily theories but theoretical
work and
um
what I
and and also that that's a very
difficult problem here that
um artificial systems are in many ways
very not like not only unlike human
beings but also unlike other animals
so whereas in research on animal
Consciousness you can try and draw some
analogies between human beings and other
animals it's less straightforward when
it comes to artificial systems and this
means that Empirical research alone will
be less helpful we also need very
sophisticated theoretical approaches to
deal with these issues and I will always
remain some uncertainty
just because artificial systems can be
so can be physically or physiologically
so different from
conscious organisms
and it's not clear how best to deal with
these uncertainties we need theoretical
approaches to make sense of all this
and I would say
we have to
we might face the
reality at some point so and maybe maybe
it turn will turn out that
we won't ever know whether certain
systems are conscious or not I'm very
skeptical that we'll someday find a
theory of Consciousness that will tell
us exactly which entities are conscious
and which are not I mean integrated
information theory is a proposal for
such a theory and it's for this reason
very important that theories like IIT
are being developed
um on the other hand it makes very
strong predictions about what kinds of
systems can be conscious and which can't
so it um would agree with the proposal I
presented here
that a computer simulation in a
classical Hardware
will not be conscious and many
artificial systems will not systems will
not be conscious even if they have all
the abilities that we that are
associated with Consciousness even if
they can
interact with the environment have
sophisticated cognitive abilities and so
on
um so
it's um
very important that such theories are
developed but I think it's also very
hard to gain certainty and maybe so this
is what I'm
some some of the
one strategy that I'm pursuing is to try
and find necessary conditions for
Consciousness which would allow us to
rule out that certain systems are
conscious
so maybe we will never have a theory of
Consciousness that says with certainty
if a system an artificial system has
Acts or x y z and so on then it is
conscious
but maybe we will have some theoretical
approaches that are empirically informed
and which strongly suggests that if a
system does not have X then it is not
conscious so maybe this will be all that
we can hope to achieve when it comes to
understanding artificial consciousness
and I see the the account that I'm
presenting here as contributing to this
project by proposing some necessary
conditions for consciousness
and as I already
indicated I'm not completely certain
about either of these conditions
but maybe something like the the weaker
condition the flow condition maybe that
would something like that
could be a useful necessary condition or
Consciousness which would rule out
Consciousness in a wide class of systems
but which would of um for example not
rule out the possibility of
Consciousness in a computer simulation
not in all computer simulations
awesome the Via negative
Consciousness studies
um so one question on measurement and
then a closing question on ethics so you
mentioned the distribution question
what is the distribution of
Consciousness in our scenario
what kind of distribution is that is it
a z-axis there's a scalar quantity that
is going to summarize the density of
some distribution in space like we were
doing some kind of topographical map or
is that distribution
[Music]
multi-dimensional are there different
dimensions to Consciousness so to what
extent do we even aim for a
uni-dimensional scalar representation
potentially
using IIT or other measures or to what
extent will we have a plurality of
Consciousness measures without
necessarily like a higher or lower
thanks um yeah that's uh very tough
question
[Music]
um
so as you already alluded to According
to some theories such as IIT
Consciousness does come in degrees but
it's um varies along a single scale the
degree of consciousness
and um classically there's also there's
distinction between the level of
Consciousness and the contents of
Consciousness or the level would be
um defined in terms of wakefulness or
vigilance
and the contents in terms of that which
is experience
and the idea would be that uh yeah you
can distinguish between levels of
consciousness
in a unidimensional way but then the
more recent proposals According to which
Consciousness is multi-dimensional and
as you already mentioned and there
which means that it may be impossible to
define a unidimensional degree of
Consciousness
um maybe you can all only order
conscious experiences along
[Music]
these different dimensions individually
but not
um have a total order on conscious
States
[Music]
yeah so I I think these are
to a large extent unresolved questions
and I don't have a strong opinion on
this but
um I do think that Consciousness at that
at least some crucial dimensions of
Consciousness that come in degrees and
I'm open to the idea that there will be
borderline cases between systems that
are
clearly conscious and systems that are
clearly unconscious
so I'm
open to the idea so the possibility that
there will be some systems for which
it's
indeterminate whether they are conscious
or not and
um apart from I mean IIT would not imply
this of course but there some some
computational approaches to
consciousness
what specify some properties I mean if
you think about the counterfactual depth
of internal representations for instance
that's something that comes in degrees
and it's not clear at what point a
system will be conscious
and cease to be unconscious what what
degree of counterfectional depth is
necessary for Consciousness and
um
yeah so I'm open to the possibility of
borderline cases of Consciousness
and
similarly it's
even if we so if we try to apply a
theories of Consciousness to other
animals than there may be cases in which
it's not clear whether what a theory of
Consciousness would say so Jonathan
Birch has a wonderful paper
about the problem of
um
trying to determine of finding out which
non-human animals are Consciousness and
the idea is that if you try to
use a theory of Consciousness that was
developed
on the basis of what we know about
Consciousness and human beings and then
maybe many cases in which it's not clear
whether the theory applies or not or
whether the conditions for Consciousness
are fulfilled or not so if you think
about global workspace Theory what is a
global workspace and we we can for human
beings distinguish between different
consuming systems local processes that
have access to the global workspace and
which receive the
contents that are represented in the
workspace and which are there by
consciously processed
but um there are animals that may that
don't have as many cognitives up
processes that don't have such
sophisticated cognitive abilities that
may maybe have something like a global
workspace but with fewer consuming
systems so when does it cease to be a
global workspace and the sense that will
be required for consciousness
and um
because of such indeterminacy it may be
more useful than to look for
um other
markers of Consciousness evidence for
Consciousness such as learning abilities
that's what uh Birch proposals
um and in part I think inspired by
work by Evangel Blanca and Simone
against
who suggests that certain forms of
learning are
transition markers for Consciousness
which provides strong evidence for the
presence of Consciousness and
um yeah what about the distribution
question so this is more about evidence
for
Consciousness and different types of
systems and
what where the distribution look like in
the end I I don't know so
um but what I'm really interested is in
trying to find out how we can determine
whether a system is conscious or how we
can rule out that a system is conscious
and what in the end this will tell us
about the distribution of Consciousness
I think is a great open question
awesome well as we say in the ant colony
the whole Nest is our workspace so
different systems will do it differently
and in closing
I know that you're teaching a course on
this so to compress it will be a
challenge but could you conclude with a
statement or actually a pair of
statements on AI ethics one addressed to
Natural humans one addressed to the
machines
um yeah so AI ethics so I don't want to
say anything about AI ethics in general
but just about
Consciousness so when it comes to human
beings
um
what I find
interesting is the question what
makes
what is required for being a moral agent
so
um most people would agree that
Consciousness gives people or gives
entities gives organisms at least some
moral status
even if it's maybe not required for
having a moral standing
um but it's at least sufficient for some
form of moral status and then maybe some
organisms matter more than other
organisms even if they are
similarly conscious or maybe
some animals matter more than other
animals because of
their cognitive abilities
and so on and and the question is what
what um
what do we have to add in order to turn
a moral patient as it were into a moral
agent a being that can
act in ways that are
not just in accordance with certain
moral principles or not in accordance
with them but they can
act because of certain moral
considerations
and is it necessary to be conscious in
order to be a moral agent
and
what I find
interesting here is to explore to what
extent accounts that look for necessary
conditions for Consciousness may also
yield some necessary conditions for
being a moral agent
so even if Consciousness may not be
required for being a moral agent maybe
there are certain necessary conditions
for Consciousness that are also
necessary for moral agency
and this can then also be applied to
artificial systems and principle
but of course when it comes to
artificial systems it's the the
interesting question is should we
even create
artificial systems that might be
conscious
or do we have a duty to create conscious
artificial systems and
my own position would be that
well in the case of animals
it's already happened we may not know
with certainty which animals are
conscious and which are not but
regardless of our epistemic situation
regardless of what we know about these
animals they are conscious or are not
conscious they feel pain or don't feel
pain they suffer they or they do not
suffer so the most we can do is to try
and minimize the suffering in existing
animals but when it comes to artificial
systems
we can at least at the moment say that
most artificial systems are
very unlikely to be conscious
and we have the unique opportunity now
to really think hard about whether we
want to risk creating conscious
artificial systems
and I think we learned at least two
things two interesting things in the
past weeks or months
about artificial systems artificial
intelligence and Consciousness and one
is that AGI may not require
Consciousness
um I think most people believe that
anyway but there was some
um I there was at least the possibility
that AGI artificial general intelligence
might require consciousness
and what we've seen with the latest
generations of language models is that
they
at least come very close to some form of
artificial general intelligence
um it's very unlikely that they're
conscious and so this gives me at least
some confidence that future more
sophisticated systems that will
have a general form of intelligence will
also not be conscious or unlikely to be
conscious and I think that's good
because it will not
that there will be
um
there will be no further incentive to
create artificial conscious systems in
order to achieve AGI because it seems
that you can achieve that without
creating conscious systems
another thing which is a bit more
concerning maybe is that
um we've we've also seen that it's very
difficult to regulate
developments in Ai and uh
big companies can just decide to put
systems on the market and make them
available for everyone and they will use
them for whatever purposes
uh without any regulation
and
so
if it will in in the maybe not too far
future be feasible to create conscious
systems if we do
um gain a better understanding of what
it would mean for an artificial system
to be conscious or maybe how to create
one people will do it and it will be
very difficult to regulate this
so this um
might be a problem for the not too far
future
a problem for a guest stream number 40.2
yes
thank you Vania very insightful best of
luck with your works and hope to talk to
you later
thank you Daniel it's been a pleasure
very well
right
foreign